Guide to the Frank Baker papers, 1641-2002 and undated, bulk 1740-1995 RL.00069
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files Series, 1641-1999 and undated, 122 boxes
  - Subject Files Series: Wesley Family Files Subseries, 1692-1997 and undated, 10 boxes
    - Charles Wesley (1707-1788)
      - Treatise on the Lord's Supper, 1849, 1990-1991 and undated (Box 135)
        Contains photocopied manuscripts from various sources.
    - Kezia Wesley (1709/10-1741)
      Youngest sister of JW and CW.
      - Correspondence, 1731-1738 (Box 135)
        Typed transcriptions of her letters to JW.
      - Miscellany: Verses, 1729, 1753, 1778, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 135)
        Photocopy and transcriptions (probably by FB) of a manuscript volume entitled "Kezia Wesley: Her Book," 1729, circa 160 pages, source undetermined. Verses apparently copied from other sources, not original, including JW poem Verses to the Memory of an Unfortunate Lady.
      - Miscellany: Verses, 1729, 1753, 1778, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 136)
    - Sarah Wesley (1726-1822)
      Wife of Charles Wesley.
      - Correspondence, notes, printed materials, and engravings 1744-1828, 1851, and undated (Box 136)
        Circa 25 transcriptions of letters, 1749-circa 1820, to Charles Wesley; Samuel Lloyd; her children, Charles, Samuel, and Sally; and others. Also includes one original engraving circa 19th century, two newspaper reproductions of engravings, circa 1823 and undated, and one manuscript leaf, one-sided (11.5 x 19 cm), "S. Wesley's Income £ 91:0:0".
    - Charles Wesley, Jr. (1757-1834)
      - Correspondence, notes, letters, printed material, 1782, 1795-1834, 1851, 1935, 1937, 1948, 1960-1965, and undated (Box 136)
    - Sarah (Sally) Wesley (1759-1828)
      - Wesley, Sarah (1759-1828), 1755, 1775-1834, 1849-1852, 1866-1867, 1932, 1948, 1983, 1992, and undated, 2 folders (Box 136)
        Contains one autograph manuscript item, signed, circa 1789. Also includes Sally Wesley's wax seal, and an unbound print article from Arminian Magazine circa 1788, "Account of Mr. C. Wesley's Death."
      - Wesley, Sarah (1759-1828) -- Letters to in BR/C-D (and some to her mother), 1758, 1788, 1795-1809, 1824, and undated (Box 136)
      - Wesley, Sarah (1759-1828) -- Correspondence with Mercy Doddridge and Adam Clarke -- from BR/C-D, 1723, 1746, 1783, 1792-1832, 1869, and undated (Box 136)
    - Samuel Wesley (1766-1837)
      - Wesley, Samuel (1766-1837), 1772, 1785, 1790, 1996, and undated (Box 137)
      - Wesley, Samuel (1766-1837) and Family, 1822, 1991-1996 (Box 137)
      - Wesley, Samuel, Musician: Kassler, Michael, 1829, 1971-1983, and undated (Box 137)
      - Wesley, Samuel (1766-1837) -- Philip Olleson, The Samuel Wesley Letters Edition, 1813, 1996-1997 (Box 137)
      - Wesley, Samuel (1766-1837), 1766, 1786-1837, 1849-1851, 1860-1864, 1876, 1951, 1966, and undated (Box 137)
    - John William Wesley (b. 1802?)
      Grandson of CW and son of Samuel Wesley (1766-1837).
      - Correspondence, 1848 (Box 137)
    - Wesley family: various topics
      Materials about multiple family members, the family in general, and other general topics. This folder group has extensive information on Wesley family genealogy and the history of various Wesleyana collections.
      - Charles Wesley, D.D., 1805-1807, 1839-1865 (Box 137)
      - Harper (nee Wesley), Emily, 1757, 1898 (Box 137)
      - Mary Wesley, undated (Box 137)
      - Wesley, Samuel Sebastian, 1946-1951, and undated (Box 137)
      - Didsbury Papers (BR/C-D and Wesley), 1697, 1730-1822 and undated, 2 folders (Box 137)
        Includes Sarah Wesley to Adam Clarke correspondence.
      - Manuscripts in shorthand, Wesley and Non-Wesley -- Colman Box, Envelope A, 1709, 1752-1762, and undated (Box 137)
      - Membership, 1742-1745 (Box 137)
      - Members, London, 1745-1746 (Box 137)
      - Members, London, 1746-1747, 1931 (Box 137)
      - Wesley Family and Investigating Wesley Family Traditions (1988, Hart238), 1703, 1858, 1876, 1895, 1980, 1987-1989, and undated (Box 138)
      - Wesley family letters, 1994 and undated (Box 138)
      - Wesley genealogy, 1747-1976 and undated, 2 folders (Box 138)
      - Wesley relics, 1909 (Box 138)
      - Wesleyana (lists, catalogues), 1867, 1889, 1897-1977 (Box 138)
        One catalogue circa 1867 and several unbound pages of catalogues listing Wesleyana, circa 19th century
      - Wesleyana collections, 1950 and undated (Box 138)
  - Subject Files Series: Card Files Subseries, 1940s-1980s and undated, 38 boxes
    Card files have been minimally identified and described, and arranged in three groups: Quotations and Concordances, Bicentennial Edition, Wesley's Library and Reading, and Other Cardfiles. Card counts are approximate, and total approximately 50,000 cards. The various files were numbered and original order has been maintained, with some changes to house like sizes together.
    - Quotations and Concordances
      - Quotations used by John and/or Charles Wesley, undated, 3500 cards (Box 139-141)
        Four files indexing quotations used by John (or perhaps Charles, at times) Wesley. The first two boxes house two files for quotations used by JW, one for English and the other for foreign languages (usually Latin); both are organized alphabetically by topic or keyword. The third box houses two more files for sources of his quotations, arranged by author. A note at the beginning of the first file indicates that Baker thought he had indexed and cross-referenced about 800 quotations in all.
      - Concordances to JW's works, 1970s-1985 and undated, 8500 cards (Box 142-147)
        Four files that somewhat complement the quotations indexes above, but also greatly expand into preparations for a general concordance. A note in the first box indicates that Baker inherited most of this unpublished work, Notes for a Wesley Concordance, from George Lawton in 1974. Lawton appears to have provided the first three indexes here, which Baker expanded at times. The first index is for aphorisms (Box 142, 250 entries). The second index is a general concordance (Boxes 142-146, 6500 entries). The third index is for proverbs and slang and colloquial expressions (Boxes 146-147, 1200 entries). Following this is a series on unlabeled cards that may be duplicates, then the concordances conclude with Baker's own index of Christian names in Wesley's writings (Box 147, 250 entries).
        Separated materials: articles by George Lawton. See folder for these indexes housed in Subject Files, Card Files Information Folders.
    - Bicentennial Edition card files and indexes
      Large set of card files that are often related to volumes of the Bicentennial Edition of the Works of John Wesley, for which Frank Baker served as General Editor. Files have been slightly rearranged to reflect the sequence of volumes in the Works. These files often complement other documents to be found in the related collection, the Wesley Works Archive.
      - Explanatory Notes upon the New Testament (Bicentennial Ed. Volumes 5-6)--alphabetical topic index, undated, 300 cards (Box 148)
      - The Methodist Societies: History, Nature, and Design (Bicentennial Ed. Vol. 9)--alphabetical by topic, undated, 700 cards (Box 148)
      - The Methodist Societies: Minutes of the Conference (Bicentennial Ed. Vol. 10), undated, 2400 cards (Box 148-150)
        Several indexes, mainly related to material that was excluded from the published volume. The first file, American Preachers (Boxes 149-150), provides the names and chronological outlines of the stationing of approximately 500 18th century Methodist preachers in the United States. Following this is a similar but much longer file for British preachers (Box 149), outlining the careers of some 1000 preachers. A keyword index to the Minutes, from 1744-1791, follows these files in Box 150; and the group concludes with a short name index of circuits in Britain. The last two files house approximately 800 and 100 entries, respectively.
      - Theological writings, Pastoral writings, and Primitive Physic, undated, 1500 cards (Box 151-152)
        Three alphabetical topic indexes for Doctrinal and Controversial Treatises, Social/Political Tracts, and one portion of Medical Writings (Bicentennial Ed. Volumes 12, 14, and 17, respectively).
      - Letters (Bicentennial Ed. Volumes 25-31) indexes and files, undated, 6000 cards (Box 152-157)
        Extensive card files that index the letters of JW in a variety of ways: chronological order; index to letters I-II; index to Letters III (in preparation as of 2011); non-Telford letters; and archival locations of Wesley letters worldwide. Baker's instructions from the first card of the extensive index of "non-Telford" letters (entries that did not appear in the previous standard version, by John Telford), give some idea of the value of this index of Wesley letters that have yet to appear in a scholarly edition: "Index, JW letters, 1756-1791. Separate card for each Name, Place, Subject. Include towns for recipients and towns from which JW wrote, but JW himself, nor recipient. List entries by date. List all names and places. List all theological subjects, scriptural quotations, historical themes, illnesses, etc...".
      - Bibliography (Bicentennial Ed. Volumes 33-34) indexes and files, undated (Box 158-165)
        Extensive card file bibliographies of Wesleyan and Methodist writing. There seem to be three bibliographies represented: one that may be preparatory for both the Bibliography volumes of the Bicentennial Edition and for editions of Baker's own A Union Catalogue of the Publications of John and Charles Wesley (3000 cards); one that is covers Methodist and Wesleyan literature and scholarship in general rather than just work by the Wesleys (12,000 cards); and one that may be a keyword index to the unpublished, partial draft of the Bibliography that Baker completed circa 1981 (700 cards). All are heavily annotated with descriptive and intellectual analysis. Card counts are approximate.
    - Wesley's library and reading, undated (books owned, inscribed, or presented by him)
      Separated materials: printed list of Wesley's library is now housed in Subject Files, Card Files Information Folders.
      - Wesley's personal library, undated, 200 cards (Box 165)
        Apparently an index of books owned by him, inscribed him (or Charles), presented by him, originally at Kingswood and Richmond. Cards record data found on specific copies.
      - Wesley's reading: anonymous and unidentified books, undated, 200 cards (Box 165)
      - Wesley's reading, clues, undated, 100 cards (Box 165)
        Roughly alphabetical by topic, though unarranged. In poor physical condition; handle with care.
    - Dissertation indexes, undated (1970s-1980s), 1000 cards
      Not labeled in detail, but these two files appear to index the dissertations of two of Baker's doctoral students, both of whom went on to become Wesleyan scholars.
      - Index labeled "Harper," probably an index of Steve Harper's 1981 dissertation, The Devotional Life of John Wesley, 1703-38 (Box 166)
      - Probably a keyword index of Richard P. Heitzenrater's 1972 dissertation, John Wesley and the Oxford Methodists, 1725-35 (Box 166)
    - Charles Wesley journals and letters, undated, 3000 cards
      Brief citation to the journal, more detailed page/date references to some unspecified edition of the letters.
      - A-Z alphabetical topic index (Box 167-169)
    - Two alphabetical unidentified files, undated, 1000 cards
      - Bibliography cards (for book?) (Box 169-170)
      - Miscellaneous background volumes and pamphlets, alphabetical by author (Box 169-170)
    - Historical Reference Index, undated, 2000 cards
      Indexes general references in manuscript and printed material, both in Baker's own collections and elsewhere. Citations are generally brief, although there is a dedicated section for JW.
      - Alphabetical card file by person, place, or topic (Box 170-171)
    - Clergy, English, undated, 200 cards
      - Small file on Methodist clergy in England (Box 172)
    - Grimshaw index, circa 1950s, 500 cards
      - Card file either for FB's dissertation or later book on William Grimshaw (Box 172)
    - Methodist letters, undated, 700 cards
      May index FB's/Duke's holdings, Methodist letters in general, or Thomas Albin's "Early Methodist Letters" (see Writings by Others Subseries).
      - Alphabetical index by author and chronological index by letter date (Box 172-173)
    - Scripture index, A-Z, undated, 2000 cards
      - Card file for FB's pastoral use: alphabetical by topic, with source of Biblical citation (Box 173-175)
    - Other card files, undated, 1000 cards
      Several small groups of cards identified only by title, or else completely unidentified.
      - Baker Collection--unidentified selection, undated (Box 175)
      - Hymnology, undated (Box 176)
      - Local histories--indexed alphabetically by place, undated (Box 176)
      - Lincolnshire towns, villages, and populations--alphabetical by place, undated (Box 176)
      - Unidentified files, undated (Box 176)
  - Subject Files Series: Oversize Materials
    - Australia, 1873 (Box OV 4)
    - Australia, 1950 (Box OV 4)
    - Baywater Circuit- map and key, undated (Box OV 4)
    - Bazaars, 1927 (Box OV 4)
    - Broadsheets and circular letter (photocopies), 1750-1834 (Box OV 4)
    - Broadsheets and circular letters (photocopies), 1791 and undated (Box OV 4)
    - Colman, 1748-1765 (Box OV 4)
    - Hull Souvenir of the Unveiling of the Fishermen's Memorial Statue, 1906 (Box OV 4)
    - Livingston, David, 1920-1929 (Box OV 4)
    - Marriott, Thomas: British Methodist Circuit Plans Collection, 1825-1826, 10 folders (Box OV 5)
    - Ordination, undated (Box OV 5)
    - Small collections, 1827-1950 (Box OV 5)
    - Wesley Anniversaries and celebrations, 1988 (Box OV 5)
    - Wesley Family Files: Charles Wesley, journals-letters, 1740-1807, 1988-1992 (Box OV 5)
    - Wesley Family Files: Charles Wesley Jr. 1782, 1795-1830, 1834, 1851, 1935, 1937, 1948, 1960-1965 and undated (Box OV 5)
    - Wesley Family Files: JW, other people named, 1741, 1951, and 1974 (Box OV 5)
    - Wesley Family Files: Seal on Matthew Lamb's letters of Deacon's Orders, 10 Aug. 1788, possibly with Wesley's thumbprint (Box OV 5)
    - World Methodist Historical Society, 1989 (Box OV 5)
      Pen and ink drawing of Frank Baker.
  - Wesley Works Editorial Project Subseries, 1700-1995 and undated, 3 boxes
    The Wesley Works Editorial Project Subseries contains Baker's files from the project office, primarily featuring photocopies and transcriptions of Charles Wesley's correspondence, and other correspondence with Charles Wesley by John Nelson, J. Langshaw, and George Whitfield. Other items include 18th century copies of the Gospel of St. Matthew and five versions of A Word in Season or, Advice to an Englishman. There are also transcriptions of the Young Students Library and Samuel Wesley's poetry, copies of Baker's schedule of Charles Wesley's letters and itinerary and John Wesley's letter locations, and transcriptions of the Thomas Illingworth diary, as well as Baker's notes on class meetings, tickets, preaching plans, along with published copies of Cirplan periodicals.
    - Gospel of St. Matthew, undated (18th century) (Box 239)
    - A Word in Season or, Advice to an Englishman, 18th century, 5 copies (Box 239)
    - Wesley/Langshaw correspondence, photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters (1729-1730s) photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters (1740s) photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters (1750s) photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters (1760s) photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters (1770s) photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters (1780s) photostats and photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters (1727-1774) photocopies and Baker transcriptions, undated, 5 folders (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters transcriptions and printed versions, undated, 3 folders (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley letters photocopies, undated, 2 folders (Box 241)
    - John Nelson to Charles Wesley letters, photocopies, undated (Box 239)
    - George Whitfield to Charles Wesley letter, transcription, undated (Box 239)
    - Young Students Library transcription, undated (Box 239)
    - Samuel Wesley poetry transcription, undated (Box 239)
    - Baker's schedule of Charles Wesley's letters, undated (Box 239)
    - Old Methodist letters in Geo. Stampe's collection, undated (Box 239)
    - Charles Wesley's Letters: A Summary, undated (Box 239)
    - Baker's Charles Wesley itinerary, undated (Box 239)
    - Class Meetings, Tickets, etc., 1905-1984 and undated (Box 239)
    - Plans, Preaching, 18th c., 1786-1980 and undated, 2 folders (Box 239)
    - CIRPLAN, 1982-1995, 2 folders (Box 239)
    - Baker lecture on Charles Wesley for Wesley Fellowship, undated (Box 240)
    - Thomas Illingworth diary, transcript, undated (Box 240)
    - Thomas Illingworth diary transcript, index and Baker notes, undated (Box 240)
    - John Wesley's letters locations, undated (Box 241)
- Teaching Materials Series, 1949-1990s and undated
  Arranged in three subseries: English Schools and Universities, Duke University, and Writings by Students.
  - English Schools and Universities Subseries, 1949-1960 and undated
    - Educational Appointments, Hull, 1951-1960 (Box 177)
    - Teaching, 1952 and undated (Box 177)
    - Department of Adult Education, Index, Hull, 1955 (Box 177)
    - Printed Materials, 1949-1959 (Box 177)
    - Hull, 1956-1960, 3 folders (Box 177)
      Includes untitled notebook, assembly agendas, register, and correspondence.
    - Holderness County Misc. Printed Materials, 1959-1960 (Box 177)
    - University of Hull, Religious Education, 1958-1960, 2 folders (Box 177)
      Includes syllabi, meeting agendas from the Board of Studies and Department of Adult Education, and printed materials
    - Hull Municipal Training College, Religious Education, 1953-1959, 2 folders (Box 177)
      Includes exam papers, syllabi, and handouts.
    - University of Hull, convocation materials and misc. agendas, 1953-1960 (Box 177)
    - Hull, visual aids, 1953, 1959, and undated (Box 177)
    - Hull, religious education, visual materials, 1958-1959 (Box 178)
    - South Holderness County Secondary School, 1958 (Box 178)
    - Kingston Upon Hull, 1959-1960, 3 folders (Box 178)
      Includes exam papers, assembly materials, syllabi, essays, courses, students, staff, meeting agendas, bibliography, and books.
    - Hull, printed materials, 1959-1960 (Box 178)
    - University of Durham and University of Hull, 1959-1960 (Box 178)
    - Hull, misc. correspondence and exam papers (Box 178)
  - Duke University Subseries, 1960-1990s and undated
    - Duke Research Council Forms, 1987-1992 (Box 178)
    - Research Council Grant, 1982 (Box 178)
    - Seminary Awards for Baker's Students, 1974-1980 (Box 178)
    - Courses Offered, 1963, 1968-1969, 1976, 2 folders (Box 178)
    - Sabbatical/Tour, 1965-1967, 2 folders (Box 178)
    - Memo on Graduate School, 1975 (Box 179)
    - Textbooks, 1985 (Box 179)
    - Misc., 1980s and 1990s (Box 179)
    - Classes Offered, 1961-1965, 1976-1977, and undated, 10 folders (Box 179)
      Includes syllabi, previous course syllabi, and handouts.
    - Correspondence, 1961-1979 (Box 179)
    - Wesley Fellows, 1984 (Box 180)
    - Wesley Fellows, 1982 (Box 180)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 180)
    - Dissertation and Thesis Proposals, 20 folders (Box 180)
    - NC Religious Education, teacher lists (Box 181)
    - Interdepartmental Misc., 1961-1985 (Box 181)
    - Interdepartmental Misc., 1961-1982, 4 folders (Box 181)
    - Career: Drafts of CVs and Publications, 1960-1977 (Box 181)
    - Frank Baker retirement, 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 181)
  - Writings by Students Subseries, 1964-1993 and undated
    Baker retained copies of a number of his students' papers at Duke, with the intent that certain of them be included in the archive for the intended "Wesley Research Centre" he mentions over the years in his correspondence and other documents. Materials in this subseries comprise a portion of that student work. Several of the students represented here went on to become prominent Wesleyan and Methodist scholars in their own right, including Richard P. Heitzenrater, who succeeded Baker as General Editor of the Wesley Bicentennial Edition. The first folder in the subseries contains a 1991 memo by Baker in which he lists many of the students and papers gathered in this subseries. Arranged alphabetically by author's surname.
    - Research papers by students for Research Centre--memo and list by Frank Baker, 1991 Mar. 18 (Box 182)
    - Arichea, Ruth, John Wesley's View and Use of Church Music, undated (Box 182)
    - Armstrong, R. Martin, A History of Hebron United Methodist Church, 1979 (Box 182)
    - Brockwell, Charles, Some Aspects of John Wesley's Doctrine of Man, 1968 (Box 182)
    - Bailes, James, The Wesleyan Doctrine of the Atonement, 1973 (Box 182)
    - Berger. Allen, A Brief History of the Kentucky District, 1976 (Box 182)
    - Bohannon, Kenneth, Baptism in Wesley's Thought, The Character and Influence of Wesley's Preaching, 1964 (Box 182)
    - Boggan, R. E., A Study of John Wesley and 18th Century Slavery, 1966 (Box 182)
    - Brannan, Emora, The Old Testament as a Source for Wesley's Eucharistic Th ought, John Wesley among the Evangelicals, 1968 (Box 182)
    - Brannan, Emora, The Presiding Elder Question, 1974 (Box 182)
    - Casto, R. Michael, Exegetical Method in the Writings of John Wesley, 1977, 2 folders (Box 182)
    - Chalker, Kenneth, Compromise and Consent: American Methodism and Slavery, 1993 (Box 182)
    - Chamberlain, Ray, The Spreading of Scriptural Holiness in Early Methodism, 1968 (Box 182)
    - Chilcote, Paul, three essays, 1978-1981 (Box 182)
      John Wesley and the Rediscovery of Antiquity: an Inquiry into the Relationship of Wesley to the Non-jurors
      A Sermon Register Compiled from Wesley's Diary
      The Women of Early Methodism: A Guide to the Literature,
    - Crim, Roger, Riverview United Methodist Church: A History of Methodism to a Common People, undated (Box 182)
    - Cross, Steven E., An Examination of John Wesley's Attitude Toward Witchcraft, 1975 (Box 182)
    - Eanes, Ralph, The Early Methodist Love Feast and its Moravian Background, 1965 (Box 182)
    - Elliott, Michael, The Significance of John Wesley's Visit to Germany, 1978 (Box 182)
    - Ferguson, Don E., The Development of Holston Methodism 1774-1788, 1971 Dec 9 (Box 182)
    - Fiorino, Albert, John Wesley's Claim to Philosophy, 1974 (Box 182)
    - Fleet, Bary, John Wesley and the Class-Meeting in the Methodist Movement, 1971 (Box 182)
    - Ford, Pamela John Wesley on Religious Education, 1975 (Box 182)
    - Frame, David, Wesley and the Deistic Controversy, Charles Wesley and the Preachers, 1966 (Box 182)
    - Gattis, William, John Wesley's Opposition to Slavery, 1970 (Box 182)
    - Gilbert, Paula, Sources of John Wesley's Social Ethic, 1978 (Box 183)
    - Giragos, John G., John Wesley, Physician of the Soul, 1978 Mar 30 (Box 183)
    - Granger, Paul, The Birth, Life, and Death of the Camp Meeting, 1976 (Box 183)
    - Gravely, William, Some Aspects of the Doctrine of Assurance in the Wesley's Hymns, 1966 (Box 183)
    - Gravely, William, The Meaning of Aldersgate in Selected Biographies of John Wesley, 1791-1891, 1966 (Box 183)
    - Guard, David, John Wesley's Theology of Baptism, 1976 (Box 183)
    - Guffey, Jennie, John Wesley's Doctrine of Perfection: with special attention to the theology..., 1975 (Box 183)
    - Hall, Elmer, Methodist Architecture 1739-1778, undated (Box 183)